Guide to the Jay Blotcher Papers MSS.137
Fales Library and Special Collections
Jay Blotcher Papers
1987-2001
Fales Library and Special Collections
Blotcher, Jay
MSS.137
4 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons, 2 card boxes, and 1 flat box.
13 audiocassettes
2 VHS
Jay Blotcher represented the lives of gay and lesbian people through his work as a journalist, publicist, freelance writer, film producer and activist. The Jay Blotcher Papers contain print, media, ephemera, and clothing materials documenting the Lesbian and Gay Rights Movement, AIDS activism and queer activism in the 1990s. The collection includes media releases and other publicity for ACT UP and Queer Nation, two major AIDS and queer advocacy organizations as well as the Anti-Violence Campaign, The American Foundation for AIDS Research (AmFAR), and several smaller organizations.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Jay Blotcher in May 2003. The accession number associated with this gift is 2003.137.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Biographical Note
Jay Blotcher represented the lives of gays and lesbians through his work as a journalist, publicist, freelance writer, film producer, and activist. His earliest work on queer activism was a feature on the Gay Student Organization in his college newspaper, The Daily Orange. Blotcher produced work on The American Foundation for AIDS Research (AmFAR), Michelangelo Signorile and numerous other individuals and grassroots organizations. In 1987, he joined ACT UP New York, represented the group at the International AIDS Conferences in Montreal, Amsterdam and Yokohama, and served as Media Coordinator for the organization from 1989-1990. Blotcher was also a founding member and Media Coordinator for Queer Nation New York, and the executive producer of the Anti-Violence Campaign. He was deeply involved in HIV/AIDS activism and queer activism in New York and internationally, both as a professional and as an activist.
Scope and Contents
The Jay Blotcher Papers (1987-2001) contain print materials, media, ephemera and clothing documenting the Lesbian and Gay Rights Movement, HIV/AIDS Activism and Queer Activism in the 1990s. The collection includes media releases and other publicity for ACT UP and Queer Nation, two major AIDS and queer advocacy organizations as well as the Anti-Violence Campaign, The American Foundation for AIDS Research (AmFAR), and several smaller organizations.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into four series:
Series I: Files and Printed Materials
Series II: Media
Series III: Ephemera
Series IV: Clothing.
Where possible, the collection retains Jay Blotcher's own organization. Materials in Series I: Printed Materials are arranged alphabetically.
Related Material at Fales Library and Special Collections
Alan Klein Papers
Michelangelo Signorile Papers
Separated Materials
Select periodicals have been separated from the collection and cataloged individually in Bobcat: "Lisp" periodical, 1995.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact NYU Special Collections (special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596) with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Audiovisual materials that have not been preserved may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact NYU Special Collections (special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596) with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Gays -- Political activity -- New York (State) -- New York.; Gay men -- United States.; Gay activists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Washington (D.C.); Yokohama (Japan); Seattle (Wash.); Vancouver (B.C.); Publicity.; In the life (Television program); New York (N.Y.).; Gays in popular culture.; AIDS activists -- New York (N.Y.); United States -- Armed Forces -- Gays.; Press releases.; Audiocassettes.; Floppy disks.; Clippings (information artifacts); Typescripts; LGBTQ+ activism; Videocassettes.; International Conference on AIDS; ACT UP (Organization); Rafsky, Bob; Signorile, Michelangelo, 1960-; AmFAR; Housing Works, Inc.; Public Impact Media Consultants; Queer Nation (Organization); Alan Klein Media Relations
- Series I: Files and Printed Materials
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains clippings, press releases and typescripts relating to Jay Botcher's work as Media Coordinator for ACT UP and Queer Nation as well as materials relating to his work as a publicist for gay and lesbian authors and organizations from 1987-2002.
  - ACT UP: Auction for Action invitation, Broadway, New York, December 3, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - ACT UP: FBI Files, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - ACT UP New York: Yokohama, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - ACT UP: Political funeral, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - ACT UP: Rafsky, Bob, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - ACT UP: Tenth anniversary action, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Activism and demonstrations, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - AIDS and queer clips. Begins September 19, 1991, ca. 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - AIDS and the media, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - AIDS education postcards, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Alan Klein Media Relations media list. September 1, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - American Foundation for AIDS Research (AmFAR): AIDS awareness campaign with Kenneth Cole, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - AmFAR: Information packet, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - AmFAR: Lordly and Dame Inc. Booking Agency, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Animal Rights. United Action for Animals and International Society for Animal Rights., 1991 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Anti-Violence Campaign, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Anti-Violence Campaign: MTV and VHI Anti-gaybashing ads, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Anti-Violence Campaign: press clips and related articles, ca. 1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - The Anti-Violence Project: Susan Sarandon public service announcement, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Astra Pharmaceutical: price inflation of AIDS drug Foscavir AIDS activists and organizations protest., 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Behrman, Andy: clippings, cards, interviews, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Behrman, Andy: "Electroboy" typescript, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Blotcher, Jay: personal media list, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Brooklyn AIDS Task Force: press release, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Canadian National AIDS Clearinghouse: postcard, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Centaur Dance Theatre, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - The Center: media releases, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Cinema, Queers and AIDS, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Comedy Central: Out There II, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Comedy Central: S. Robbe, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - d'Adesy, Anne-Christine, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Donat, Hank "Popcorn in the Morning" typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - A few good queers, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - The Flirtations. Gay musical group., 1992 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Gay City Health Project, Seattle Washington, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD): Mediagram campaign, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - GLAAD: Trojan War, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - "Gotham gals hanker for other hunks" [Jay Blotcher quoted in article] New York Post. July 16, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - "Hallowe'en Mystery" by Jay Blotcher, grade 5. Martin E. Young School, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Harry Paul and Associates letterhead, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Hennelly, Christopher: Police brutality case, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Hetrick-Martin Institute: Volunteer orientation packet, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Housing Works "Demonstrators Slam Lack of AIDS Housing" Newsday article. September 13, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - "In the Life" media releases, clippings and program guides, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Institute for Gay and Lesbian Strategic Studies. Working group on funding. "Creating Communities: Giving and Volunteering by Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, and Transgender People.", 1998 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - International Conference on AIDS. Postcard for the 11th conference, Vancouver Canada. July 7-12, 1996. (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - "Johnny Guitar" with Ryan Landry and Kandi Kane. Presented by the Gold Dust Orphans Antro Theatre, Provincetown MA, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Lesbian and Gay Directory of Services and Resources, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Lesbian and Gay People of Color Steering Committee Participating Organizations, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Lesbian and Gay Teachers Association Media advisory, undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Media Mavens resources list. November 17, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Military Murders, Gay Ban, Petrelis in Japan, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Mr. Leather New York -- Organizing committee certificate of recognition, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - National Lesbian and Gay Journalists Association convention. "Making Waves" Hyatt Regency, Miami FL. September 5-8, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - National Gay and Lesbian Task Force. Press release, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - New York Advertising and Communications Network membership directory, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - NYC Parents and Friends of Lesbians and Gays [PFLAG] salutes Dick Ashworth. May 11, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Nocturnal, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Outfest. Los Angeles Gay and Lesbian Film Festival, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Out Loud lesbian and gay cultural and business expo., 1994 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - "Out There" comedy special, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Out Write: the fifth national lesbian and gay writers conference., 1995 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Percy William. "Outing: Shattering the Conspiracy of Silence", 1994 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Planet Q: The Queer Comedy Troup. "Homo Alone, Lost in Colorado", 1993 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - POZ: Health, Hope and HIV. March 1997. (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Project Inform: treatment information packet., undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Public Impact Media Consultants: queer media list, August 1994. (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Queer Nation, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Queer Nation letterhead, undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Rainbow Run for the end of AIDS, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Reed, Phillip. City Council candidate, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - RFSL: the Swedish Federation for Gay and Lesbian Rights. "Lesbian and Gay the Swedish Way.", 1994 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Sadownick, Douglas. "Sacred Lips of the Bronx" press packet., undated (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Senior Action in a Gay Environment (SAGE) Dance Marathon at the Limelight., 1991 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - SAGE Dance Marathon at the Roxy., 1992 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - SAGE tribute to Lorenz Hart, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Sedarbaum, Ed. New York State Senate campaign, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Sex Information and Education Council of the US (SEICUS) Study Guide #2: Homosexuality., undated (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - "Sex is...exploring the meaning of sex and sexuality..." Film by Marc Huestis and Lawrence Helman., 1993 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: columns, undated (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: "Life Outside" Armistead Maupin quote., 1997 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: publicity for "Life Outside", undated (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: "Life Outside" typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: "Outing Yourself" News from Randomhouse, undated (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: "Outing Yourself" project planner, multiple dates (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: "Outing Yourself" typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: "Queer in America" College tour bookings., 1995 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: "Queer in America" press packet, undated (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: "Queer in America" typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: Speaking engagements, undated (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Television, Queers and AIDS, undated (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - United Voices, United Visions committee lists, June 10, 1995. (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - "Voices from the Front" Frameline release, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - "When AIDS Ends" by Andrew Sullivan, New York Times Magazine, November 10, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - "Wilde" special screening invitation, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 95)
- Series II: Media
  Audio cassettes, microcassettes, floppy disks and videocassettes containing articles, interviews, music and programs relating to Jay Blotcher's activism and interests.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Audiovisual and born-digital materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
  - The Glass Spider Tour, David Bowie in Concert. Giants Stadium, NJ August., undated (Box 3, Audiocassette 137.0001)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
    Original format: Microcassette, Sony MC60
  - Burroughs Welcome Coverage, April 25, 1989 (Box 3, Audiocassette 137.0002)
    Original format: Microcassette, AIWA MC-30
  - MacLeod, undated (Box 3, Audiocassette 137.0003)
    Original format: Microcassette, Maxell MC-60
  - Meat Puppets and Marianne Faithfull, undated (Box 3, Audiocassette 137.0004)
  - Mildred Pierced, May 11, 1987 (Box 3, Audiocassette 137.0005)
  - Rollerena, undated
    - Part 1, Tape 1, cuid44121 (Box 3, Audiocassette 137.0006)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Format: Microcassette, AIWA MC-30; Duration: 61 minutes; Preservation Note: Very poor audio.
    - Part 1, Tape 2, cuid44122 (Box 3, Audiocassette 137.0007)
      Format: Microcassette, Sony MC60; Duration: 107 minutes; Preservation Note: Very poor audio.
  - Phone Messages, July and September, 1991 (Box 3, Audiocassette 137.0008)
    Original format: Microcassette, TDK
  - Phone Messages, undated; cuid44120 (Box 3, Audiocassette 137.0009)
    Original format: Microcassette, Panasonic RT-30MC
  - Unlabeled tape, 1994-1996 (Box 3, Audiocassette 137.0010)
    Original format: Microcassette, Panasonic MC-30
  - Unlabeled tape, undated (Box 3, Audiocassette 137.0011)
    Original format: Microcassette, TDK MC60
  - Alternet Gay and Lesbian Radio for South Florida: Program #26, March 7, 1993 (Box 3, Audiocassette 137.0012)
    Original format: Audiocassette, TDK D60
    Scope and Contents
    Label reads: "Adoption ban for gays ruled unconstitutional in Sarasota; Florida lawmaker from Davie withdraws civil rights bill; Navy claims gay sailor was murdered by gay ex-lover; California city legally defines 'family'; This gay in history did it on stage: Colin Higgins; A report on gay women in the military; Making an artistic statement: art about AIDS; To buy or not to buy: that is the question of boycotts; Music: Hosework! and Dykes!!"
  - Larry King Show, Michelangelo Signorile, May 19, 1993 (Box 3, Audiocassette 137.0013)
    Original format: Audiocassette, unmarked
  - ACT UP on 60 Minutes, featuring Peter Staley, Bob Rafsky and Marina Alvarez, November 15, 1992 (Box 3, Vhs 137.0014)
  - Video compilation of erotica in mainstream TV and film by SF journalist Jim Provenzano / Jay's Jo Jumpin Joy Juice Jumble, undated (Box 3, Vhs 137.0015)
    Note on tape says: "Tape snapped, needs mending"
  - Outweek articles and Tetris, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    3.5 inch floppy disk, unlabeled
  - Outweek, SYR Mag Files, Games files, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    3.5 inch floppy disk, 3M double side 1.0 MB
  - Resume 1995, Applications and Utils., Out Mag pieces, Out Loud expos, GAA reunion, Comedy Skits, Miles, Lisp, New article ideas, 1260 LSM, Splash (Box 3, Folder 1)
    3.5 inch floppy disk, TDK MF-2HD
  - Queer in America, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    3.5 inch floppy disk, Fuji film, MF2DD
  - Queries, Joey Pons 2145, Cruse, Out-Gean, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    3.5 inch floppy disk, 3M DS, HD 1.4 Mb
  - Sex Club Article, complete; profile of Howard Cruse, January 29, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    3.5 inch floppy disk, HD
    Currently unavailable until duplication occurs.
  - Sex Clubs, Howard Cruse article, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Series III: Ephemera
  Materials including pins, nametags, pens and magnets relating to Jay Blotcher's activism and professional work for Queer Nation, ACT UP and the Lesbian and Gay rights movement.
  - Square button. "ACT UP Fight Back Fight AIDS", undated (Box 4)
  - Circular button. "Queer in America", undated (Box 4)
  - Circular button. "He's Gotta Have It!", undated (Box 4)
  - Circular button, missing pin. "Try 31. For a Change. WNYC-TV" Paper pink triangle with words "our time" pasted on., undated (Box 4)
  - circular button. "Silence=Death", undated (Box 4)
  - Rectangular button. "Rainbow Run for the End of AIDS San Francisco to Vancouver. June 7th-August 4th 1990. In Honor of Tom Waddell and Keith Haring." (Box 4)
  - Circular button. "Hot Sex Now", undated (Box 4)
  - Circular button. "Ramrod Anniversary XVI", undated (Box 4)
  - Circular button. [Trans activist, Marsha P. Johnson], undated (Box 4)
  - Circular button. "ACT UP", undated (Box 4)
  - Circular button. "Silence=Mort 1989 Silence=Death project" (Box 4)
  - Lighter, undated (Box 4)
  - Rectangular sticker. "PM Chretien We're Dying for a National AIDS Strategy", undated (Box 4)
  - 30 round stickers. "Queer in America", undated (Box 4)
  - Postcard from the Beverly Prescott hotel. " 'When a shower just won't do' The Beverly Prescott's King Jacuzzi Room", undated (Box 4)
  - Rectangular Magnet. "The Pants Too? Yes, Please Donate. Out of the closet thrift store and AIDS healthcare foundation.", undated (Box 4)
  - XI International Conference on AIDS nametag. "Jay Blotcher- The Front Page" With Durex pen., undated (Box 4)
  - Necklace. One side "ACT UP for a cure" Opposite side "1992 March on Washington for Lesbian, Gay and Bi Equal Rights and Liberation." (Box 4)
  - One pencil. " 'Pageant' - NY's Nightly Beauty Contest", undated (Box 4)
  - One pen. "Wolf Talk Radio 1490AM, 96.7 FM", undated (Box 4)
- Series IV: Clothing
  Series IV contains t-shirts and a sweatshirt related to Jay Blotcher's professional career, activism and interests. All of series IV is located in Box 5, which is an OVERSIZE box.
  - T-shirt. "Q" "Queer Nation", undated (Oversize 5)
  - T-shirt. "Some of my best friends are Queer in America", undated (Oversize 5)
  - T-shirt. Photograph. [Liam Neeson], undated (Oversize 5)
  - Sweatshirt. "Queer Nation get used to it!", undated (Oversize 5)